<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Act against false musters and free quarters, and anent due paying of their Majesties forces. At Edinburgh, the ninth of May 1693.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Parliament. Committee of Estates.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05153</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1025B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R183849</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52529188</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52529188</idno>
            <idno type="VID">178877</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05153)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178877)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2774:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Act against false musters and free quarters, and anent due paying of their Majesties forces. At Edinburgh, the ninth of May 1693.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Parliament. Committee of Estates.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the heir of Andrew Anderson, Printer to their most excellent Majesties,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>With royal seal at head of text.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Extracted forth of the records of Parliament, by Tarbat. Cls. Registri.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland. --  Army --  Pay, allowances, etc. --  Law and legislation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Soldiers --  Scotland --  Billeting --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="act">
            <pb facs="tcp:178877:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QUI MALY PENSE</q>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure> 
               <hi>ACT</hi> Againſt falſe Musters and free Quarters, and anent due Paying of Their Majeſties Forces.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>At <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> 
                  <date>the ninth of <hi>May</hi> 1693.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UR SOVERAIGN LORD and LADY, the King and Queens Majeſties, and the Eſtates of Parliament, taking to their Conſideration, that it will contribute much to Their Majeſties Service, that all Fraud and Deceit in making of falſe Muſters, be obviated &amp; prevented, &amp; that the Pay deſtinat and appointed to the Souldiers be not kept up by their Officers and others, intruſted with the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Souldiers, but that their Pay be effectually given them. Therefore, the King and Queens Majeſties and Eſtates of Parliament, Statutes and Ordains, that if any Perſon, Officer, or other of Their Majeſties Forces, as well in Caſtles and Garriſons as Others, ſhall make, or give, or procure to be made or given, or make uſe of any falſe or untrue Certificat, thereby to excuſe any Souldiers for their abſence from any Muſter or other Service, which they ought to attend or perform, upon a pretence of ſickneſs or other cauſe, that then every Perſon ſo making, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, or procuring ſuch Certificats, ſhall be fyned for every ſuch offence, in the Sum of one thouſand Merks, the one half to Their Majeſties uſe, and the other half to the Informer, and if he be an Officer that contraveens, he, beſide the fine of one thouſand Merks, ſhall be Caſhiered and Diſplaced, and ſhall be Incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of any Military Office or Imployment within this Kingdom, and every Officer that ſhall make any falſe or untrue Muſter of Man or Horſe, and every Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſary, Muſter-maſter, and other Officer, that ſhall allow or ſign the Muſter-roll, wherein ſuch falſe Muſters is contained, ſhall be Caſhiered and loſs their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and ſhall be Incapable of any Military Office or Imployment, within this Kingdom, and ſhall likewiſe, be fyned in the Sum of one thouſand Merks, the one half to Their Majeſties uſe, and the other half to the Informer, and for the more effectual preventing of falſe Muſters, Statutes and Ordains, that every Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary or Muſter-maſter, upon any Muſter to be made, ſhall be obliged, to give notice a convenient time before, to the Magiſtrats of the Burghs, or Sheriffs of the Shyres, or their Deputs, or Baillies of Royalty or Regality, or their Deputs, or Stewarts of Stewartries, or their Deputs, within whoſe Juriſdictions the Muſter is to be made, and the Magiſtrats of the Burgh, in caſe the Muſter be to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:178877:2"/>be made within a Burgh, and the Sheriff or their Deputs, when the Muſter is to be made within a Sheriffdom, and the Baillie of the Regality or his Deputs, when the Muſter is to be made within a Regality, and the Stewart of the Stewartries or their Deputs, when the Muſters is to be made within a Stewartry, to be preſent at every ſuch Muſter, and give their utmoſt Aſſiſtance, for the diſcovering of any falſe or untrue Muſter, and every Commiſſary or Muſter-maſter, that ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect to give notice as ſaid is, or ſhall refuſe to take the Aſſiſtance of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats of Burghs, when the Muſter is made within a Burgh, or of the Sheriffs, Baillies of Regalities and Royalties, and Stewarts, or their Deputs, when the Muſter is made within their reſpective Juriſdictions, the Commiſſary or Muſter-maſter ſo offending, ſhall loſs his Office, and be fined in the Sum of one thouſand Merks, the one half to Their Majeſties uſe, and the other half to the Informer, and no Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-roll ſhall be allowed, unleſs the ſame be ſigned by the Magiſtrat of the Burgh, or Sheriff of the Shyre, or Baillies of Regalities and Royalties, or Stewarts or their Deputs, within whoſe Juriſdictions the Muſter is made, and if any perſon ſhall be falſly muſtered, or offer himſelf falſly and deceitfully to be muſtered, upon Certificat thereof under the hand of the Muſter-maſter, or chief Magiſtrat of the place, who ſhall be preſent at the muſtering, he ſhall be Impriſoned for the ſpace of a Moneth, &amp; ſhall have his right ear cut off; &amp; if any Perſon ſhall wittingly &amp; wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, lend or furniſh a Horſe to be muſtered, which ſhall not truly belong to the Trooper, or Dragooner, or Troop muſtered, the ſaid Horſe ſo falſly muſtered, ſhall be Forefaulted to the Informer, if the Horſe doth belong to the Perſon, Lending or Furniſhing; and if the Horſe do not belong to the Lender or Furniſher, he ſhall be fined in the Sum of five hundred Merks, to be payed to the Informer, and if he be an Officer that Lendeth or Furniſheth a Horſe to be muſtered, which doth not truly belong to the Trooper or Dragooner muſtered, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſuch Officer ſo offending, ſhall be fined in the Sum of five hundred Merks, to be payed to the Informer, which ſhall be payed out of the Arrears of the ſaid Officers Pay, by the Order of the Court-martial to the Pay-maſter, if the ſaid Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer ſhall have any Arrears due to him; and if there ſhall be no Arrears due to the ſaid Officer, the Court Martial ſhall immediatly give Order, to ſeize the Goods of the ſaid Officer, and ſell them for payment of the Fyne, which is to be given to the Informer, the Superplus that is more than pays the ſaid Fyne, being alwiſe reſtored to the Owner; and if the Officer ſo offending, ſhall have no Goods, that then he ſhall be committed to Priſon, there to remain for the ſpace of ſix Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, and the Court Martial ſhall diſcharge the Informer, if he be a Souldier, from any further Service, if he demand the ſame, and if any Pay-maſter, or Clerk of any Regiment, Troop, or Company, ſhall detain and withhold by the ſpace of a Moneth, the pay of any Officer or Souldier, (Cloaths and all other juſt Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowances being deduced,) after the Pay ſhall be received; or if any Officer having received their Souldiers Pay, ſhall refuſe to pay every common Souldier their reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pective Pay, when it ſhall become due, the Pay-maſter, Clerk, or Officer ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending, ſhall loſs his Office or Imployment, and ſhall be fined in two thouſand Merks, to be payed to the Informer, and to be raiſed in manner foreſaid, and ſhall be Incapable of any Office or Imployment, Civil or Military within this Kingdom, and the Informer, if a Souldier, ſhall be diſcharged of any further Service, if he demand the ſame. And it is further Statute &amp; Ordained, that the commanding Officer of every Troop or Company, at the time of Muſter, ſhall bring in a Cetificat ſigned of the number of ſuch Perſons, as are ſick, or have leave to abſent upon Foreloffs, and of ſuch as are dead and deſerted ſince the laſt Muſter, with the days of their deaths or deſertions; and if ſuch Certificats ſhall prove falſe, the Officer ſigning ſuch a Certificat, ſhall be lyable to the ſame pain, as in the caſe of falſe Muſters: As alſo it is Provided, that if any Officer, Commiſſary, or Muſter-maſter, ſhall Muſter any perſon that is a Servant, or receives Wages from any Officer, or that ſhall attend any Officer as a Servant, in the abſence of the ſaid Officer from his
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:178877:3"/>Quarters, or ſhall Muſter any perſon by a wrong Name, the ſaid Officer, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſary, or Muſter-maſter ſhall be puniſhed as in the caſe of falſe Muſters. And it is further Statute and Ordained, that no Pay-maſter of the Army, Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, or Muſter-maſter, or their Deputs and Servants, ſhall receive any Fees, or make any Deductions whatſomever out of the Pay of any Officer or Souldier, other then the uſual Deductions for Cloathing, under the Pain of being puniſhed as in the caſe of falſe Muſters; and it is Declared, that the Pay-maſter of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Commiſſary, or Muſter-maſter, ſhall be lyable to the ſame Pain and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in caſe of Contravention, by their Deputs and Servants, as if they had done it themſelves; and as the Officers and Souldiers ſhould be effectually payed, and not defrauded of their due Pay, ſo it is juſt and reaſonable that they pay the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and not be allowed to exact free Quarter where they come. Therefore, and for freeing the Country of other Abuſes and Diſorders in uſe to be Committed by the Souldiers, The King and Queens Majeſties, and the Eſtates of Parliament, Ratifies, Approves and Confirms an Act of Privy Council, of the date the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day of <hi>February</hi> laſt, one thouſand ſix hundred ninety three, <hi>anent the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of the payment of Proviſions for the Forces, and Redreſsing Abuſes commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them,</hi> in the whole Heads, Tenors and Contents thereof; and Ordains the ſame to take full effect, and to be put to further execution, of the which Act the Tenor follows, <hi>William</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> by the Grace of GOD, King and Queen of <hi>Great-Brittain, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defenders of the Faith, To</p>
            <p>Macers of Our Privy Council, Meſſengers at Arms, Our Sheriffs in that part, conjunctly and ſeverally, ſpecially Conſtitute, Greeting. Foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as by divers Laws and Acts of Parliament made by Our Royal Predeceſſors, all free Quartering of Souldiers in tranſient or local Quarters, and all Localities for furniſhing or carrying Corn, Straw, Hay, or Graſs to Souldiers Horſes, is expreſly Prohibited and Diſcharged; and by an Eſtabliſhment under Our Royal Hand, there being Meaſures laid down, and Fonds appropriat for the exact and punctual payment of the ſtanding Forces and Gariſons within this Our antient Kingdom, and a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſary appointed for making due and regular Proviſions of Corn, Straw and Graſs, for the Horſes and Dragoons preſently under Our Pay, and in Our Service with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Our antient Kingdom, by ready Money, or otherwiſe as he can beſt Bargain with any of Our Leidges for their Corn, Straw and Graſs: Whereby the Abuſes heretofore done and committed upon any of Our Leidges, by the Illegal exacting Locality or free Quarter, may be Remeeded and Prevented, and all Mens meat, and Horſe-meat furniſhed to any Officers or Souldiers in Our Service within this Our antient Kingdom, duely payed. And We conſidering how neceſſary it is, that all Our good Subjects ſhould know by whom, and in what manner they are to be payed for all Proviſions of Corn, Straw and Graſs, for Horſes, and Meat and Drink to be furniſhed to Our Officers and Souldiers, by them or any of them; and that all Officers and Souldiers within this Our ſaid antient Kingdom may go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern and regulat themſelves, and the Troops under their Command accordingly, as they will be anſwerable. We with Advice of the Lords of Our Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, Require and Command the Commiſſary-General, appointed and received by the Lords of Our Theſaury, to make due and timeous Proviſions of Oats, Straw and Graſs, for all Horſe and Dragoons at preſent under Our Pay, and in Our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice within this Our antient Kingdom, in their reſpective, tranſient and local Quarters: And that the ſame may be more orderly and effectually done, We Require and Command all Our Officers, who command the ſaid Troops, to give timely Notice to the ſaid Commiſſary of their Removal to, and from local Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and of the Rout appointed for their March in tranſient Quarters, that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions may be ready accordingly. And in caſe any Parties be called to March u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſudden Commands, which may not be fit to impart to the Commiſſary: Then We with Advice foreſaid, ſtrictly Charge and Require the Commanders of the ſeveral Parties, to buy with ready Money the Oats, Straw and Graſs, neceſſary
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:178877:4"/>for their Horſes, as any other of Our Leidges is in uſe to do, and what he ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purſe or expend thereon: We hereby Require and Command Our ſaid Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to refound and repay the ſame. And We with Advice of Our Privy Council, do hereby Require and Command Our Commiſſary-General by himſelf, or fit Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons imployed and intruſted by him, to attend at the Magazines which ſhall be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for Our Troops at their reſpective Quarters, two Hours each Day, <hi>viz.</hi> betwixt ten and twelve in the Forenoon, at the leaſt to attend the two Hours above-named upon one or moe days of each Week, ſuch as ſhall be particularly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon betwixt the Commiſſary and the Officers, to the effect, the Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may be given out by the Commiſſary, and received by the Officers or Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers timeouſly, and without Diſorder or Confuſion, and hereby all Officers and Souldiers are peremptorly Prohibited and Diſcharged to offer any Injury or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe to Our ſaid Commiſſary or his Deputs, as they will be anſwerable at their higheſt Peril. And ſicklike, We with Advice foreſaid, peremptorly Require and Command the Officer Commanding in Cheif, in any place of local or tranſient Quarters, to ſee the whole Meat and Drink furniſhed to the Souldiers and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers under his Command, by the Land-Lords of their Quarters, exactly and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly payed at the ordinary Rates of the Countrey: And in caſe there ſhall be any Exaction or Diſcharge of free Quarters extorted, or Abatement exacted below the ordinary Rates, or any other Abuſe Committed; We with Advice foreſaid, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire and Command the Commanding-Officer there for the time, to make pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by ready Money for the whole Souldiers and Officers on the place in their lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Quarters, once every Week at fartheſt, and tranſient Quarters before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveal, if they ſtay a ſhorter time than a Week, under the pain of Caſheiring and breaking the ſaid Commanding Officer, upon Complaint of his tranſgreſſing the Premiſſes, to be made the Party injured to Our Privy Council, or to the Sheriff, or his Deput, Bailie of Regality, or his Deput, Stewart of the Stewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, or his Deput, or any two Commiſſioners of Supply of the Bounds and Shire, where the ſaids Abuſes and Injuries are done and committed, whom or either of whom: We with Advice foreſaid, Require and Command, to receive the ſaids Complaints, and tranſmit the ſame to the Clerks of Our Privy Council, within ten days after any ſuch Complaints ſhall be made to them, under the pain of being lyable to repair the Party injured themſelves, and which Complaints, We with Advice foreſaid, appoint to be purſued by our Advocat and Sollicitor upon the publick Charge. And in caſe any privat Party ſhall think fit to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the ſamine themſelves, We hereby Require and Command the Expences that ſhall be laid out by them; In Proſecution thereof, to be Repayed and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imburſed to them by the Lords of Our Theſaury, als well as the Expences to be laid out by Our Sollicitor, all which are to be retained and deduced by the ſaids Lords of Our Theſaury, out of the Officers Pay, againſt whom the ſaid Complaint is made and verified. And in caſe any inferiour Officer in Tranſient or Local Quarters, ſhall Tranſgreſs any of the Premiſſes; We hereby Require and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the commanding Officer, upon Complaint made to him and proven, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to pay the Complainer what ſhall be due to him, and if the Perſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained on, be an uncommiſſionat Officer, the ſaid Commander is inſtantly to break and Caſheir him, and if he be a Commiſſionat-officer, who ſhall ſo Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs; We with Advice foreſaid, Require the ſaid Commanding-officer, to Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend him in the mean time, and immediatly to Repreſent the ſame to Our Privy Council, that they may give Orders for Breaking and Caſheiring the Officer tranſgreſſing, providing the Complaints for not payment of Local-quarters, or committing any of the Abuſes foreſaid therein, be made to the ſaid Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding-officer, within eight days after a weeks Quarters are reſting, or any other Abuſes committed, and in Tranſient-quarters; before the Parties removeal, with certification, if payment be not craved; or Complaints made within the time foreſaid, the Commanding-officer shall be free, but prejudice to the Land-lords
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:178877:5"/>and others, to ſeek their Payment and Reparation from the Perſons Debitors therein, or Committers thereof, by all other legal means, and it shall be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient evidence, that the Commanding-officer has been complained to, and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to make payment of Proviſions furnished to Souldiers, Men, and Horſes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Command, or redreſs Abuſes committed by them, if the ſame be made to him, in preſence of a Magiſtrat within Burgh, a Juſtice of Peace or two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes. And We with Advice foreſaid, do Declare, that no Diſcharges, shall be ſufficient for exonering the Souldiers and Officers; and inſtructing the payment of their Quarters, unleſs they be Subſcribed by the Maſter of the Ground, or his Chamberlain, or the Officer of the Ground before two Witneſſes, or a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat within. Burgh. And for preventing of a common Abuſe done and committed upon our Leiges, by Souldiers and Officers, in their marches Preſſing and Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon Horſes, for their own privat Uſe and Service. We with Advice fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, do ſtrictly Prohibit and Diſcharge all preſſing or ſeaſing upon Horſes by any Officer or Souldier, for their own particular and privat Service, under the pain of a moneths Pay, to be retained (upon complaint to be made and inſtructed as aforeſaid) off the Officer who commands, and where Horſes are neceſſary for carrying Artillary, Amunition, or Proviſion, or any other uſe of the Army, in the Towns, or in the Countrey, that the ſame be imployed and made uſe of, by order of the Commander of the Party, and of the Magiſtrats of the Burghs joint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; If the Horſes be furniſhed within Burgh: And by the ſaid Commander, and any one of the Commiſſioners of Supply within the Shire, where the Horſes are furniſhed and made uſe of in Landwart. And We with Advice foreſaid, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the third Act, Parliament One Thouſand ſix Hundred and Eightie one, ordain that there be payed for each day, that the ſaids Horſes ſhall Travel, three ſhilling Scots for each two miles to the Man and Horſe, and each day that they do not Travel, ſix ſhilling Scots to the Man, and as much for the Horſe, the Man being obliged to provide himſelf and the Horſe, which ſhall be payed by the Magiſtrats of the Burgh: if the Horſes be taken within a Town, or if in the Countrey, by the Collector of the Supply in the Shire, who are to be Repayed thereof, or to have the ſame allowed to them by the Receiver-general. And that the Horſes neceſſary to be made uſe of, and imployed for the Service, and uſe of our Forces above expreſſed, may be the more Regularly and Equally proportioned and provided: We with Advice foreſaid, Require and Command the Magiſtrats within Burghs, and Commiſſioners of Supply, and Juſtices of Peace in Landwart, to cauſe provide from time to time a competent number of Horſes, within their reſpective Bounds, for the Service of our Forces, and uſes foreſaids, as they will be anſwerable at their Peril. And We with Advice fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, Prohibit and Diſcharge any Officer or Soldier to Seaſe upon, or Preſs any Horſes, without the concourſe of the Perſons above-named, or to detain them longer than one days March at fartheſt; but to reſtore and give back the ſaids Horſes, imployed in the manner foreſaid in good caſe, under the pain of a months Pay to be retained in manner foreſaid, off the Officer who shall be found to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traveen the Premiſſes, beſides the payment of the Price of the Horſe to the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisher, as the ſame shall be inſtructed before the Bailies within Burgh, Sheriffs, Stewarts, Bailies of Regalities, or Deputs, or Juſtices of Peace in the Countrey. And to the end, Our Royal Pleaſure in the Premiſſes, may be made publick and known. OUR WILL IS, and We Charge you ſtrictly and Command, that incontinent theſe Our Letters ſeen, ye paſs to the Merkat Croſs of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and all other Mercat Croſſes of the Head-burghs of this Kingdom, als well Royalty as Regalitie and Stewartrie, and other places needful, and there in Our Name and Authority, by open Proclamation, make publication of the Premiſſes: And likewiſe, that all Our Forces as well as our Leidges, may have notice hereof. We do Require and Command, theſe preſents to be publictly read, at the Head of every Troop, and Company of our ſtanding Forces, that none may pretend
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:178877:6"/>ignorance. Given under Our Signet at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> the fourteenth day of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary,</hi> and of Our Reign the fourth year, one thouſand ſix hundred and ninety three. With this Addition, that in the caſe of either local or tranſient Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; if any Officer, or Souldier ſhall not make due payment, conform to the ſaid Act of Privy Council, of what they take on in their Quarters, or ſhall commit any Abuſes in their Quarters, it ſhall be lawful and leiſum to the Land-lord, upon whom the Souldier was quartered, to inſtruct before a Juſtice of Peace, or a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner of Exciſe and Aſſeſſment, Magiſtrat of Burgh, or the next Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Heretor, by Witneſs, or the Oath of the Party leſed, what was taken on by the Officers or Souldiers, or what Damages were done by them in their Quarters; which being inſtructed, and liquidat as ſaid is, the Juſtice of Peace, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner of Exciſe and Aſſeſſment, Magiſtrat of Burgh, or the Neighbouring Heretor, before whom the Value of the ſaid Quartering or Damage ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed &amp; liquidat, ſhall be holden &amp; obliged to give the Land-lord, upon whom the Officer or Souldier were quartered; a Declaration bearing the value of the Quartering and Damages ſuſtained: And Ordains the Collector of the Shire to give Allowance of the ſame to the Land-lord, out of the fore-end of his Ceſs or Exciſe; &amp; that the Collector of the Shire ſhall have allowance thereof from the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Receiver: And in caſe the Land-lord be a Tennent, or other perſon that is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lyable for Ceſs or Exciſe; In this Caſe, the Heretor of the Ground ſhall have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of the ſame, out of the fore-end of his Ceſs or Exciſe, due and payable by him, to the effect that the Tennent may get payment thereof. And Ordains the Collectors of the Ceſs and Exciſe, to give allowance to the Land-lord, or He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retor of the Ground of the Sum that ſhall be contained in the ſaid Declaration out of the fore-end of the Land-lord or Heretors Ceſs or Exciſe, and the Col<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lectors are appointed to give account thereof to the General Commiſſary, or pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter of the Army, that he may retain the ſame off the fore-end of the Officer or Soldiers Pay. And it is hereby declared, that if the Officer firſt applyed to, as is appointed by the foreſaid Proclamation, ſhall not give Redreſs, then the Officers Pay ſhall be lyable as well as the Souldiers Pay, and the Collector and General Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver ſhall give allowance accordingly, and the Collector and General Receiver, are ordained to give the ſaid allowance, under the pain of Deprivation, by and attour the reſounding of the Damage of the Partie leſed. And Ordains this Act to be publickly read upon the head of every Regiment, Troop, or Company, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time the ſame is muſtered, that due Obedience may be given thereto.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Extracted forth of the Records of Parliament, by</hi> TARBAT. <hi>Cls. Regiſtri.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>
               <hi>God ſave King</hi> VVilliam <hi>and Queen Mary.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Printed by the Heir of <hi>Andrew Anderſon,</hi> Printer to their moſt Excellent Majeſties, <hi>Anno</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
